Slavery/Anti-Slavery Collection, 1791-1968
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Slavery and anti-slavery collection
1791-1968
MS 390
3 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection primarily documents abolitionist activism. Materials include correspondence; addresses; essays; sermons; deeds from the sales of female slaves; photographs of emancipated slaves; and numerous articles on the escaped slave William Wells Brown. A substantial portion of the collection documents abolitionist John Brown and his descendents. Other individuals represented in the collection include Jonathon Edwards, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Lucretia Mott, members of the Garrison family, Angelina Grimke, Daniel Webster, Emma Willard, Maria Weston Chapman, and Henry B. Blackwell. Also represented are various anti-slavery societies.
This collection consists primarily of material that documents abolitionist activism from 1791 to 1865. Original source material includes abolitionist publications, annual reports, correspondence, addresses, conference proceedings, essays, newspaper clippings, photographs, and sermons. Individuals represented in the collection include Jonathon Edwards, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Lucretia Mott, members of the Garrison family, Angelina Grimké, Daniel Webster, Emma Willard, Maria Weston Chapman, and Henry B. Blackwell.
Included in the collection are records of the Providence (R.I.) Anti-Slavery Society, 1833-43; the proceedings of the Anti-slavery Convention of American Women in Philadelphia in 1838; the eighth annual report of the Boston Female Anti-slavery Society from 1841; Jonathan Edwards's 1791 sermon "The Injustice and Impolicy of the Slave Trade and the Slavery of the Africans"; deeds from the sales of female slaves from 1820 and 1858; photographs of emancipated slaves; and numerous articles by W. Edward Farrison on the escaped slave William Wells Brown.
A substantial portion of the collection relates to abolitionist John Brown and his descendents. that document abolitionist John Brown and his descendents. These include articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, and letters from the Garrison family to Brown's widow and sons and various essays examining myths about John Brown and the historical reality of his motivations and actions.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
Materials in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy all copyright holders. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Abolitionists--United States--History; African Americans--History--To 1863--Sources; Anti-slavery movements--United States--History--Sources; Slavery--United States--History--Sources; Women abolitionists--United States--History; Brown, John, 1800-1859; Brown, William Wells, 1815-1884; Edwards, Jonathan, 1703-1758--Sermons; Garrison family; Grimke, Angelina Emily, 1805-1879; Grimke, Sarah Moore, 1792-1873; Mott, Lucretia, 1793-1880; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852
Additional Information
Related Material
Associated material located in the Garrison Family Papers, in the Sophia Smith Collection.
- GENERAL
  - American Anti-Slavery Almanac (volume 1, #1 -original and use copy), 1836 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anti-Slavery Convention (Philadelphia, 1838): proceedings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anti-Slavery: articles and pamphlets, 1791-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Deeds for the sale of a girl slave, 1820, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Liberator: articles and reprints (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of slaves and emancipated slaves; propaganda, and drawings, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- INDIVIDUALS
  - John Brown
    [See Box 2]
  - William Wells Brown
    - Lecture to Female Anti-Slavery Society of Salem, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pamphlets by Edward Farrison, 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Maria Weston Chapman: letter to Miss Hilditch, circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sarah and Angelina Grimke, Archibald Grimke: article, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thomas T. Stone: address before Female Anti-Slavery Society of Salem, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - George Francis Train: speech in reply to Charles Sumner, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    [See Flat File]
  - Harriet Tubman: Jailbreak Out of History: A re-Biography of Harriet Tubman by Butch Lee, 2000 (Box 1)
- ORGANIZATIONS
  - Boston Female Anti-Slavery Society: annual reports, 1836, 1840, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ladies New York Anti-Slavery Society: "Appeal to the Christian Women of America," 1836 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Massachusetts Anti-Slavery Society: annual reports, 1847-49, 1852, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - New Haven Anti-Slavery Society: constitution, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rochester Ladies Anti-Slavery Society: annual report, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Vigilance Committee of Boston: article by Wilbur H. Siebert, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Tolles, Frederick B., Slavery and the "Woman Question": Lucretia Mott's Diary, 1840 Supplement 23 to Journal of the Friends Historical Society (Friends Historical Association: Pennsylvannia, 1952)
  - Providence Anti-Slavery Society: constitution and records, 1833-43 (Box 1a)
- JOHN BROWN
  - A Bibliography of John Brown, by Thomas Featherstonhaugh (includes handwritten copy and published pamphlet), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Articles, clippings, and photos (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - John Brown Family, Jason Brown, and John Brown Fund: letters, articles, and research (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Jeannette Lee: notes (Box 2, Folder 23)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Carroll Slave Emancipation Document,1858 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thomas J. Nast: Reconstruction cartoons, circa 1870s (Map-case Flat File)
  - George Francis Train: speech in reply to Charles Sumner (original and use copy), October 16, 1862 (Map-case Flat File)